13 He passed out of the room and began the ascent, Basil hallwood following
close behind. They walked softly, as men do instinctively at night. The lamp cast
fantastic shadows on the wall and staircase. A rising wind made some of the windows
rattle. When they they reached the top landing, Dorian set the lamp down on the
floor, and taking out the key, turned it in the lock. “You insist on knowing, Basil?” he
asked in a low voice.
“Yes.” “I am delighted,” he answered, smiling.
Then he added, somewhat harshly, “You are the one man in the world who is entitled
to know everything about me. You have had more to do with my life than you think”;
and, taking up the lamp, he opened the door and went in.
A cold current of air passed them, and the light shot up for a moment in a
flame of murky orange. He shuddered. “Shut the door behind
you,” he whispered, as he placed the lamp on the table hwood glanced around him with a puzzled
expression. The room looked as if it had not been lived in for years. A faded
Flemish tapestry, a curtained picture, an old Italian casone and an almost empty bookcase
that was all that it seemed to contain, besides a chair and a table. As Dorian
Gray was lighting a half-burned candle that was standing on the mantle shelf he
saw that the whole place was covered with dust and that the carpet was in
holes. A mouse ran scuffling behind the wains skating There was a damp odor of
mildew. “So you think that it is only God who sees the soul, Basil? Draw that
curtain back, and you will see mine.” The voice that spoke was cold and
cruel. “You are mad, Dorian, or playing a part,” muttered hallwood frowning. “You
won’t? Then I must do it myself,” said the young man, and he tore the curtain from
its rod and flung it on the ground. An exclamation of horror broke
from the painter’s lips as he saw in the dim light the hideous face on the canvas
grinning at him. There was something in its expression that filled him with
disgust and loathing. Good heavens! it was Dorian Gray’s own face that he was
looking at! The horror, whatever it was, had not yet entirely spoiled that
marvelous beauty. There was still some gold in the thinning hair and some
scarlet on the sensual mouth. The Soden eyes had kept something of the loveliness of their
blue, the noble curves had not yet completely passed away from chiseled
nostrils and from plastic throat. Yes, it was was Dorian himself. But
who had done it? He seemed to recognize his own brush work and the frame was his own
design. The idea was monstrous, yet he felt afraid. He seized the lighted candle,
and held it to the picture. In the leftand corner was his own name, traced
in long letters of bright vermilion. It was some foul parody, some
infamous ignoble satire. He had never done that. Still, it was his own picture
picture. He knew it, and he felt as if his blood had changed in a moment from fire
to sluggish ice. His own picture! What did it mean? Why had it
altered? He turned and looked at Dorian Gray with the eyes of a sick man. His
mouth twitched, and his parched tongue seemed unable to
articulate. He passed his hand across his forehead. It was dank with clammy sweat.
The young man was leaning against the mantle Shelf watching him with that
strange expression that one sees on the faces of those who are absorbed in a
play when some great artist is acting. There was neither real sorrow in
it nor real joy. There was simply the passion of the spectator, with perhaps a
flicker of triumph in his eyes. He had taken the flower out of his coat, and was
smelling it, or pretending to do so. “What does this mean?” cried holwood at
last. His own voice sounded shrill and curious in his
ears. “Years ago, when I was a boy,” said Dorian Gray, crushing the flower in his
hand, “you met me, flattered me, and taught me to be vain of my good
looks. One day you introduced me to a friend of yours, who explained to me the
wonder of youth, and you finished a portrait of me that revealed to me the wonder of
beauty. In a mad moment that, even now, I don’t know whether I regret or
not, I made a wish, perhaps you would call
it a prayer....” “I remember it! Oh, how well I remember it! No! the thing is impossible.
The room is damp milu has got into the canvas. The paints are used had some
wretched mineral poison in them. I tell you the thing is impossible.” “Ah, what is impossible?”
murmured the young man, going over to the window and leaning his forehead against
the cold Mis stained glass.
“You told me you had destroyed it.” “I was wrong. It has destroyed me.” “I don’t
believe it is my picture.” “Can’t you see your ideal in it?” said Dorian
bitterly. “My ideal, as you call it...” “As you called it.” “There was nothing evil in it,
nothing shameful. You were to me such an ideal as I shall never meet again. This
is the face of a SATA It is the face of my soul.”
“Christ! what a thing I must have worshiped It has the eyes of a
devil.” “Each of us has heaven and hell in him, Basil,” cried Dorian with a wild
gesture of despair holwood turned again to the portrait and gazed at it. “My God!
If it is true,” he exclaimed, “and this is what you have done with your life, why,
you must be worse even than those who talk against you fancy you to be!” He held
the light up again to the canvas and examined it. The surface seemed to be
quite undisturbed and as he had left it.
It was from within, apparently, that the foulness and horror had come. Through
some strange quickening of inner life the leprosis of sin was slowly eating
the thing away. The rotting of a corpse in a watery grave was not so
fearful. His hand shook, and the candle fell from its socket on the floor and
lay there sputtering. He placed his foot on it and put it out. Then he flung
himself into the rickety chair that was standing by the table and buried his face in his
hands. “Good God, Dorian, what a lesson! What an awful
lesson!” There was no answer, but he could hear the young man sobbing at the
window. “Pray, Dorian, pray,” he murmured. “What is it that one was taught to say in
one’s boyhood? ‘Lead us not into temptation. Forgive us our sins. Wash away our
iniquities.’ Let us say that together. The prayer of your pride has been answered.
The prayer of your repentance will be answered also. I worshiped you too much. I
am punished for it. You worshiped yourself too much. We are both punished.”
Dorian Gray turned slowly around and looked at him with tear dimmed eyes. “It
is too late, Basil,” he faltered. “It is never too late, Dorian.
Let us kneel down and try if we cannot remember a prayer. Isn’t there a verse
somewhere, ‘Though your sins be as scarlet, yet I will make them as white as
snow’?” “Those words mean nothing to me now.” “Hush! Don’t say that. You have done enough
evil in your life. My God! Don’t you see that accursed thing learing at
us?” Dorian Gray glanced at the picture, and suddenly an uncontrollable feeling
of hatred for Basil hallwood came over him, as though it had been suggested to
him by the image on the canvas, whispered into his ear by those grinning
lips. The mad passions of a hunted animal stirred within him, and he loathed the
man who was seated at the table, more than in his whole life he had ever
loathed anything. He glanced wildly around. Something glimmered on the top of
the painted chest that faced him. His eye
fell on it. He knew what it was. It was a
knife that he had brought up, some days before, to cut a piece of cord, and had
forgotten to take away with him. He moved slowly towards it, passing hallwood as he
did so. As soon as he got behind him, he seized it and turned round hallwood
stirred in his chair as if he was going to rise. He rushed at him and dug the
knife into the great vein that is behind the ear, crushing the man’s head down on
the table and stabbing again and again. There was a stifled groan and the
horrible sound of someone choking with blood. Three times the outstretched arms
shot up convulsively, waving grotesque stiff fingered hands in the air. He
stabbed him twice more, but the man did not move. Something began to trickle on the
floor. He waited for a moment, still pressing the head down. Then he threw the
knife on the table, and listened. He could hear nothing, but the
drip, drip on the threadbear carpet. He opened the door and went out on the
landing. The house was absolutely quiet.
No one was about. For a few seconds he stood bending over the ballustrade and
peering down into the black seething well of darkness. Then he took out the key and
returned to the room, locking himself in as he did so. The thing was still seated in the
chair, straining over the table with bowed head, and humped back, and long fantastic
arms. Had it not been for the red jagged tear in the neck and the clotted black
pool that was slowly widening on the table, one would have said that the man was simply
asleep. How quickly it had all been done!
He felt strangely calm, and walking over to the window, opened it and stepped out
on the balcony. The wind had blown the fog away, and the sky was like a
monstrous peacock’s tail, starred with myriads of golden eyes.
He looked down and saw the policeman going his rounds and flashing the long
beam of his lantern on the doors of the silent houses. The crimson spot of a
prowling handsome gleamed at the corner and then vanished. A woman in a fluttering Shaw
was creeping slowly by the railings, staggering as she went. Now and then she
stopped and peered back. Once, she began to sing in a hoarse voice. The policeman
strolled over and said something to her.
She stumbled away, laughing. A bitter blast swept across the square. The gas
lamps flickered and became blue, and the leafless trees shook their black iron
branches to and fro. He shivered and went back, closing the window behind
him. Having reached the door, he turned the key and opened it. He did not even
glance at the murdered man. He felt that the secret of the whole
thing was not to realize the situation.
The friend who had painted the fatal portrait to which all his misery had
been due had gone out of his life. That was enough. Then he remembered the lamp.
It was a rather curious one of Moorish workmanship, made of dull silver inlaid
with arabes of burnished steel, and studded with coarse
turquoises. Perhaps it might be missed by his servant, and questions would be
asked. He hesitated for a moment, then he turned back and took it from the
table. He could not help seeing the dead thing. How still it was! How horribly
white the long hands looked! It was like a dreadful wax
image. Having locked the door behind him, he crept quietly downstairs. The woodwork creaked and
seemed to cry out as if in pain. He stopped several times and waited. No: everything was
still. It was merely the sound of his own footsteps. When he reached the library, he
saw the bag and coat in the corner. They must be hidden away somewhere. He
unlocked a secret press that was in the Wayne sitting a press in which he kept
his own curious disguises, and put them into it. He could easily burn them
afterwards. Then he pulled out his watch.
It was 20 minutes to two. He sat down and began to think. Every year— —every month, almost—
—men were strangled in England for what he had done. There had been a madness of
murder in the air. Some red star had come too close to the earth.... And yet, what
evidence was there against him? Basil hallwood had left the house at 11: No
one had seen him come in again. Most of the servants were at Selby Royal. His
valet had gone to bed....
Paris! Yes. It was to Paris that Basil had gone, and by the midnight train, as he had
intended. With his curious reserved habits, it would be months before any
suspicions would be roused.
Months! Everything could be destroyed long before then. A sudden thought struck
him. He put on his fur coat and hat and went out into the hall. There he paused,
hearing the slow heavy tread of the policeman on the pavement outside and
seeing the flash of the bullseye reflected in the window. He waited and held his
breath. After a few moments he drew back the latch and slipped out, shutting the
door very gently behind him. Then he began ringing the bell. In
about 5 minutes his valet appeared half dressed and looking very
drowsy I'm sorry to have had to wake you up, Francis,” he said, stepping in; “but I had
forgotten my latch key What time is it 10 minutes past 2 sir,” answered the man,
looking at the clock and blinking 10 minutes past 2 How horribly late! You
must wake me at 9: tomorrow I have some work to do.” “All right, sir.” “Did anyone call
this evening?” “Mr hallwood sir. He stayed here till 11 and then he went away to catch his
train.” “Oh I'm sorry I didn’t see him. Did he leave any message?” “No, sir, except that
he would write to you from Paris, if he did not find you at the club.” “That will
do, Francis. Don’t forget to call me at 9: tomorrow No,
sir.” The man shambled down the passage in his slippers. Dorian Gray threw his hat and
coat upon the table and passed into the library. For a quarter of an hour he
walked up and down the room, biting his lip and thinking. Then he took down the
Blue Book from one of the shelves and began to turn over the
leaves. “Alan Campbell, 152 Hartford Street, Mayfair.” Yes; that was the man he wanted I CHAPTER